Guide to the Arthur Bliss Lane Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur Bliss Lane papers
1904-1957
MS 5
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
47.5
The papers consist of official, personal, and business correspondence, articles, speeches, clippings, recordings, photographs, and other papers of Arthur Bliss Lane, career diplomat, public servant, and lecturer. The papers reflect Lane's diplomatic career from the time he entered the service in Rome (1916), until his resignation as Ambassador to Poland (1947), and contain correspondence from international political figures. Also included are materials relating to his work on behalf of Poland, anti-communism, and the Republican Party.
Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1894-1956
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Arthur Bliss Lane, 1957, 1969, and 1970.
Arrangement
Arranged in ten series and one addition: I. Letters to Arthur Bliss Lane, Letters to Cornelia Baldwin Lane, 1907-1957, II. Letters From Arthur Bliss Lane, 1904-1956, III. Documentary Materials, 1919, 1943-1946, IV. Personal Materials, 1916-1952 1954, 1956, V. Writings, 1941, 1947-1956, VI. Printed Matter, 1929-1956, VII. Press Releases, 1947, 1949-1953, VIII. Newspaper Clippings, 1920-1925, 1936-1956, IX. Photographs, 1894, 1917-1922, 1925-1930, 1933-1934, X. Phonograph Records, 1950, 1952.
Scope and Contents
The Arthur Bliss Lane Collection consists of official, personal, and business correspondence, articles, speeches, clippings, photographs, and recordings for the period 1904-1957. The bulk of the collection is the correspondence to and from Arthur Bliss Lane (1894-1956). Approximately one half of the correspondence covers the period of his youth and diplomatic service; and the other, that of his retirement.
After graduation from Yale, Arthur Bliss Lane entered the diplomatic service in 1916 in Rome, where he acted as private secretary to Ambassador Thomas Nelson Page until August 1917, and then as 3rd secretary of the Embassy until April 1919. Lane was 2nd secretary in Warsaw while Hugh Gibson was Ambassador, April 1919-December 1920. While stationed in London from December 1920 to September 1922, he served as 2nd secretary, under Ambassador George Brinton McClellan Harvey, and as secretary to the United States Delegation at the 1921 meeting of the Supreme Council in Paris. Lane then acted as secretary of the Legation in Berne until his return to the United States in March 1923. The relatively limited correspondence for this period includes a number of letters, notes, and documents.
Upon his return to the Department of State, Arthur Bliss Lane worked in the Division of Western European Affairs. From May 1924 to July 1925 Lane held the position of assistant to the Undersecretary of State, Joseph C. Grew. Lane was 1st secretary to the Embassy in Mexico City, August 1925 to November 1927; he served as chief of the Division of Mexican Affairs until March 1930, and as counselor of the Embassy in Mexico City until July 1933. There is considerable correspondence with Hershel V. Johnson, who succeeded Lane in 1928 as 1st secretary and as chief of the Division of Mexican Affairs, in 1930 and with Ambassadors (to Mexico) Dwight W. Morrow (1927-1929), J. Reuben Clark (1930-1933), and Josephus Daniels (1933-1941).
In July 1933 Lane became the youngest career Minister in the diplomatic service, and from December of that year to May 1936 he was in Nicaragua. During this period Lane became friendly with Anastasio Somoza and President Juan Sacasa, and was concerned with the alleged assassination of Sandino. The correspondence includes letters and telegrams from fellow diplomats and Nicaraguan officials.
Lane served as Minister to Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania from June 1936 to September 1937, at which time he was transferred to Yugoslavia. He remained in Belgrade until the German occupation of April 1941. During his Riga tour, Lane's correspondence includes conversations with Vilhelm Munters, the Latvian Foreign Minister, and exchanges between Lane and the Moscow Embassy. While in Yugoslavia, Lane became friendly with Prince Paul, the Regent; his correspondence reveals close attention to the influence of Italy and Germany.
During the Second World War Arthur Bliss Lane was Minister to Costa Rica, October 1941 to April 1942, and Ambassador to Columbia, until October, 1944. During these assignments one of his chief concerns was the Proclaimed List of Axis firms and sympathizers.
His Polish assignment was Arthur Bliss Lane's last. He was Ambassador near the Polish Government in London, October 1944 to May 1945; in May 1945 he became Ambassador to the Polish Government in Warsaw. In March 1947, Lane resigned in protest over the then recent elections in Poland in which the Communists claimed victory. Lane's correspondence from this period is largely with American diplomats, persons seeking news of Polish relatives, and Polish primates.
From April 1947 until his death in August 1956, Arthur Bliss Lane undertook a number of lecture tours, radio programs, articles and letters by which he worked to stimulate public opposition to theactivities of the Soviet Union, particularily in Eastern Europe. In his speeches and writings, and in his book I Saw Poland Betrayed, Lane denounced both the spirit of the Yalta Agreement and the manner in which it was carried out. He became a critic of the Roosevelt Administration and of the Democratic Party.
During this period, Arthur Bliss Lane was a member and participant in many Polish charities and anti-Communist organizations, including committees supporting the investigation of the Katyn Forest Massacre. Lane campaigned vigorously in 1952 among the Slavic ethnic groups for the Republican Party and Dwight D. Eisenhower. After 1952, he urged diplomatic relations with the Vatican.
The correspondence from the period of Lane's retirement is voluminous; represented are admirers, representatives of Polish and other minority group organizations, various charitable committees, members of Congress and of the Administration, and old friends.
[See Yale University Library Gazette, October 1957, for article on Arthur Bliss Lane.]
Among the persons referred to in this collection are the following:
*Acheson, Dean Gooderham, 1893-
*Anders, Wladyshaw, 1892-
*Andrews, Frank Marwell, 1884-1943
*Armour, Norman, 1887-
*Atherton, Ray, 1883-
*Baldwin, Ruby (Colburn), 1862-1950
Barnes, Maynard B., (1945-1946)
*Baruch, Bernard Mannes, 1870
*Benson, Ezra Taft, 1899-
*Benton, William, 1900-
*Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-
Berry, Burton, U. S, mission to Rumania (1946)
*Bierut, Boleslaw, President of Poland, 1892-1956
Bilmanis, Afred, Latvian Envoy to U. S. (1936)
*Bloom, Sol, 1870-1949
Boal, Pierre del, (1941-1942)
*Bohlen, Charles Eustis, 1904-
Bonsal, Phillip Wilson, (1942-1944, 1946)
*Bowers, Claude Gernade, 1878-
*Braden, Spruille, 1894-
*Brett, George Howard, 1886-
Brugere, Raymond, French diplomat (1940-1941, 1945-1946)
*Bullitt, William Christian, 1891-
*Byrnes, James Francis, 1879-
*Caffery, Jefferson, 1888-
*Calderon, Guardia, Rafael Angel, President of Columbia, 1900-
Calderon, Ramirez Salvador, Nicaraguan Ambassador to Mexico (1933-1934)
*Cambon, Paul, French Ambassador to Great Britain, 1843-1924
*Campbell, Sir Ronald Ian British Minister to Yugoslavia, 1890-
*Cavendish-Bentinck, Victor Frederick William, British Ambassador to Poland, 1897-
*Churchill, Winston, 1871-1947
*Clark, Joshua Reuben, 1871-
*Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933
*Corrigan, Frank, 1881-
*Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948
*Daniels, Paul Clement, 1903-
*Davies, Joseph Edward, 1876-
*Davis, Elmer, 1890-
*Davis, John William, 1873-1955
Davis, Monnett B. (1943)
Dawson, Allan (1936-1938, 1942)
De bayle, Henri, Nicaraguan diplomat (1934-1936)
Dickson, Samuel S. (1933)
*Donovan, William Joseph, 1883-
*Dubinsky, David, 1892-
*Dulles, Allen Welsh, 1893-
*Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959
*Dunn, James Clement, 1890-
Durbrow, Elbridge (1945-1946)
Early, Steve (1933)
Eberhardt, Charles Christopher (1933)
*Eisenhower, Dwight David, 1890-
Ekis, Ludvigs, Latvian Finance Minister (1937, 1940)
*Elbrick, Charles Burke, 1908-
Erhardt, John G., Political Advisor in Austria (1946)
Espinosa, Rodolfo R.
*Farley, James A., 1888-
*Ferguson, Homer, 1889-
*Finletter, Thomas Knight, 1893-
Fitch, Aubrey Wray, Deputy Chief of Naval Operations (1945)
Fotitch, Constantin, Yugoslavian Ambassador to the U.S. (1942)
Frazer, Robert (1941-1942)
*Gibson, Hugh, 1883-1954
*Gonzales, Antonio Cornelius
Gonzales, Fernandez, Columbian Foreign Minister (1942)
*Gordon, George Anderson, 1885-
Grady, Henry F. (1939)
*Grew, Joseph Clark, 1880-
*Gunther, Franklin Mott, 1885-1941
*Hanna, Mathew Elting 1873-1936
*Harding, Warren Gamaliel, 1865-1923
*Harriman, Averell, 1891-
*Harrison, Leland, 1883-1951
*Harvey, George Brinton Mc Clellan, 1864-1928
Hawks, Stanley, and Margaret (Baldwin)
*Helen, queen Consort of Rumania, 1896-
Helouis, George E. J., French diplomat, (1944-1947)
*Henderson, Loy Wesley, 1892-
*Herter, Christian Archibald, 1895-
*Hicks, C. D.
*Hildking, John H., 1895-
*Hoover, Herbert, 1874-
*Hoover, John Edgar, 1895-
*Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948
*Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955
*Hunting-Wilson, Francis Mairs, 1875-
*Ickes, Harold Le Claire, 1874-1952
Johnson, Eric A., President U. S. Chamber of Commerce (1943)
*Johnson, Hershel V. 1894-
Kaczmarek, Cieslaw, Bishop of Kielce (1945-1946)
Keith, Gerald (Many letters 1942-1947)
*Kellogg, Frank Billings, 1856-1937
*Kennan, George Frost, 1904-
*Kennedy, John Fitzgerald, 1923-
*Kennedy, Joseph Patrick, 1888-
La Guardia, Fiorello Henry (1942)
*Lane, James Warren, 1864-1927
*Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928
*Lay, Julius Gareche, 1872-1939
Lebiediew, W. Z., Soviet Ambassador to Poland (1946)
*Lehman, Herbert H., 1878-
*Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1902-
*Lord, Robert Howard, 1885-
*Long, Boaz Walton, 1876-
*Long, Breckinridge, 1881-
*Lopez, Alfonso, President of Columbia, 1886-
MacArthur, Douglas, 2nd (1946)
McCafferty, William J. (1933-1934)
*McIntyre, James Francis Aloysius, Cardinal 1886-
*Mac Murray, John Van Antwerp, 1881-
McNarney, Joseph T., General (1946)
*Mac Veagh, Lincoln, 1890- *Mathews, H. Freeman, 1899-
*Mayer, Ferdinand Lathrop, 1887-
*Messersmith, George S., 1883- *Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw, Premier of Poland, 1901-
Moffat, J. Pierrepont (1937-1942)
*Montgomery, John Flournoy, 1878-1954
Moore, R. Walton (1937)
Morrow, Elizabeth (Cutter), (1930-1931, 1933, 1935, 1941-1942, 1945)
*Morrow, Dwight Whitney, 1873-1931
*Mundt, Karl Earl, 1900-
*Munters, Vilhelm, 1898-
*Murphy, Robert Daniel, 1894-
Newson, H. Dorsey (1942)
Nichols, Acosta
*Ninde, Margaret (Lane), -1947
Norweb, R. Henry (1913, 1947)
*Olds, Robert Edwin, 1875-1932
*Orlando, Victorio Emanuele, Premier of Italy, 1860-1952
*Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922
*Parrish, Robert H.
*Patterson, Richard Cunningham, 1886-
*Paul, Prince, Regent of Yugoslavia, 1893-
*Pearson, Drew, 1897-
*Peter II, King of Yugoslavia, 1923-
*Phillips, William, 1878-1951
*Picardo Michalski, Theodoro, President of Costa Rica, 1900-
Pilja, Milivoj, Yugoslavian Foreign Minister (1939)
*Pinkley, Vergil, 1907-
Puig Casauranc, Jose M., Mexican Foreign Secretary (1933)
Ratton, Eugene, French diplomat (1942-1944)
Redfern, Gilbert, UNRRA mission to Poland (1946)
*Robbins, Warren Delano, 1885-1935
*Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich, 1908-
*Rodzinski, Artur, 1894-1958
*Roosevelt, Eleanor (Roosevelt), 1884-
*Roosevelt, Franklin Delano 1882-1945
Rowe, Leo S., Pan American Union (1927-1928, 1931, 1933-1936, 1942)
*Rubinstein, Artur, 1889-
*Sacasa Sacasa, Juan Bautista, 1874-
*Sack, Leo, 1889-1956
Sapieha, Adam, Cardinal (1945-1946)
*Santos, Eduardo, President of Columbia, 1888-
Sanz de Santamaria, Carlos, Columbian Minister of National Economy (1944)
Sarepera, Ernst, Estonian Foreign Minister (1937)
Satterwaite, Joseph (1936-1937, 1940, 1943)
*Sayre, Francis Bowers, 1885-
Scandett, Richard B. UNRRA mission to Byelorussia (1946)
*Schoenfeld, Hans Frederick Arthur, 1889-1952
*Scotten, Robert Mc Gregor, 1891-
Seymour, Charles (1937-1939, 1942)›
*Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616
*Sharps, William Graves, 1859-1922
*Shaw, Gardiner Howland, 1893-
*Sheffield, James Rockwell, 1864-1938
Shirer, William L., Correspondent (1939)
Sierra, Manuel, Mexican Foreign Minister (1935)
Simmons, John Farr, 1892- (1936)
*Skinner, Robert P., 1866-
Smith, Francis
*Smith, Walter Bedell, 1895-
*Somoza, Anastasio, 1896-1956
*Sonnino, Sidney, 1847-1922
*Spellman, Francis Joseph, Cardinal, 1889-
Spivak, Lawrence E. (1947)
*Sterling, Frederick Augustus, 1876-1957
*Stettinius, Edward, 1900-1949
*Stevenson, Adlai Ewing, 1900-
Stewart, James B. (1943)
*Stimson, Henry Lewis, 1867-1950
*Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-
*Sulzberger, Cyrus Leo, 1912-
*Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-
*Summerlin, George Thomas, 1872-1947
Taft, Charles P. (1945)
*Taft, William Howard, 1858-1931
*Taylor, Wayne Chatfield, 1893-
*Thompson, Dorothy, 1894-
*Thompson, Llewellyn, E., 1904-
Tittman, Harold, (1938-1939, 1942-1943)
Tovanovitch, Slobodan, Yugoslavian Prime Minister in Exile, (1942)
*Truman, Harry S., 1884-
Tuck, Somerville Pinkney (1936, 1944)
*Tully, Grace G.
Vasse, M. L., Free French diplomat (1942-1943)
*Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-
*Wallace, Hugh Campbell, 1863-1931
*Walsh, Harry L.
*Weddell, Alexander, W., (1941)
*Welles, Sumner, 1892-
*White, Henry, 1850-1927
*Wiley, Alexander, 1884-
*Wiley, John Cooper, 1893-
*Wilson, Charles Stetson, 1883-
*Wilson, Henry Lane, 1857-1932
Wilson, Hugh, (1938)
Wilson, Orme, (1943-1944, 1947)
*Winiewicz, Josef, Polish Ambassador to U.S., 1905-
*Wright, James H.
*Wright, Joshua Butler, 1877-1939
* means that correspondence is catalogued.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Bliss Lane was born in Brooklyn, New York on June 16, 1894. He graduated from Yale University (B.A., 1916) and entered the diplomatic service as secretary to the United States ambassador to Italy. Lane served in diplomatic posts throughout Europe, and joined the Department of State in 1923. He served in Mexico and Nicaragua before returning to Europe in 1937. Lane served as ambassador to Colombia (1942-1944) and ambassador to Poland (1945-1947). He retired from diplomatic service in 1947 and wrote and lectured extensively. Lane was an active member of anti-communist groups and served on the American Committee to Investigate the Katyn Massacre (1949-1952). He died in New York City on August 12, 1956.
Anti-communist movements; Diplomatic and consular service, American; Emigration and immigration; Katyn Massacre, Katynʹ, Russia, 1940; Colombia -- Foreign relations; Costa Rica -- Foreign relations; Estonia -- Foreign relations; Europe; Latin America; Latvia -- Foreign relations; Lithuania -- Foreign relations; Mexico -- Foreign relations; Nicaragua -- Foreign relations; Poland -- Foreign relations; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- Politics and government; Yugoslavia -- Foreign relations; Photographs; Diplomats; Elena, Princess, consort of Carol II, King of Romania, 1896-; Pavle, Prince of Yugoslavia, 1893-1976; Petar, King of Yugoslavia, II Karađorđević, 1923-1970; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Anders, Władysław, 1892-1970; Andrews, Frank Maxwell, 1884-1943; Armour, Norman, 1887-1982; Atherton, Ray, 1883-1960; Baldwin, Ruby Colburn, 1862-1950; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Benson, Ezra Taft, 1899-1994; Benton, William, 1900-1973; Berle, Adolf A., Jr., 1895-1971; Bierut, Bolesław, 1892-1956; Bloom, Sol, 1870-1949; Bohlen, Charles E. (Charles Eustis), 1904-1974; Bowers, Claude G. (Claude Gernade), 1879-1958; Braden, Spruille, 1894-1978; Brett, George H. (George Howard), 1886-1963; Bullitt, William C. (William Christian), 1891-1967; Byrnes, James F. (James Francis), 1882-1972; Caffery, Jefferson, 1886-1974; Calderón Guardia, Rafael Angel, 1900-1970; Cambon, Paul, 1843-1924; Campbell, Ronald Ian, 1890-1983; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Clark, J. Reuben, Jr., 1871-1961; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Corrigan, Francis P. (Francis Patrick), 1881-1968; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948; Daniels, Paul C. (Paul Clement), 1903-1986; Davies, Joseph Edward, 1876-1958; Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958; Davis, John W. (John William), 1873-1955; Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982; Dulles, Allen, 1893-1969; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959; Dunn, James C. (James Clement), 1890-1979; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Elbrick, C. Burke, 1908-1983; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976; Ferguson, Homer, 1888-1982; Finletter, Thomas K. (Thomas Knight), 1893-1980; Gibson, Hugh, 1883-1954; Gonzalez, Antonio C. (Antonio Cornelius), 1888-1965; Gordon, George A. (George Anderson), 1885-1959; Grew, Joseph C. (Joseph Clark), 1880-1965; Gunther, Franklin Mott, 1885-1941; Hanna, Mathew Elting, 1873-1936; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Harrison, Leland, 1883-1951; Harvey, George Brinton McClellan, 1864-1928; Henderson, Loy W. (Loy Wesley), 1892-1986; Herter, Christian Archibald, 1895-1966; Hicks, C. D.; Hildring, John H., 1895-; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948; Hull, Cordell, 1871-1955; Hunting-Wilson, Francis Mairs, 1875-1946; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Johnson, Herschel V., 1894-1966; Kellogg, Frank B. (Frank Billings), 1856-1937; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kennedy, Joseph P. (Joseph Patrick), 1888-1969; Lane, Arthur Bliss, 1894-1956; Lane, James W. (James Warren), 1864-1927; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928; Lay, Julius Gareche, 1872-1939; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963; Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1902-1985; Long, Boaz Walton, 1876-1962; Long, Breckinridge, 1881-1958; López, Alfonso, 1886-1959; Lord, Robert Howard, 1885-1954; MacMurray, John Van Antwerp, 1881-1960; MacVeagh, Lincoln, 1890-1972; Matthews, H. Freeman, 1899-1986; Mayer, Ferdinand L. (Ferdinand Lathrop), 1887-1986; McIntyre, J. Francis A. (James Francis Aloysius), 1886-1979; Messersmith, George S. (George Strausser), 1883-1960; Mikołajczyk, Stanisław, 1901-1966; Montgomery, John Flournoy, 1878-1954; Morrow, Dwight W. (Dwight Whitney), 1873-1931; Mundt, Karl E. (Karl Earl), 1900-1974; Munters, V. (Vilhelms), 1898-1967; Murphy, Robert D. (Robert Daniel), 1894-1978; Ninde, Margaret Lane, -1947; Olds, Robert Edwin, 1875-1932; Orlando, Vittorio Emanuele, 1860-1952; Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922; Parrish, R. H. (Robert H.); Patterson, Richard C., Jr. (Richard Cunningham), 1886-1966; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969; Phillips, William, 1878-1968; Picado M., Teodoro (Picado Michalski), 1900-1960; Pinkley, Virgil, 1907-1992; Portland, Victor Frederick William Cavendish-Bentinck, Duke of, 1897-; Robbins, Warren Delano, 1885-1935; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Rodzinski, Artur, 1892-1958; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Rubinstein, Artur, 1887-1982; Sacasa, Juan Bautista, 1874-1946; Sack, Leo R., 1889-1956; Santos, Eduardo, 1888-1974; Sayre, Francis Bowes, 1885-1972; Schoenfeld, Hans Frederick Arthur, 1889-1952; Scotten, Robert McGregor, 1891-; Sharp, William Graves, 1859-1922; Shaw, Gardiner Howland, 1893-1965; Sheffield, James R. (James Rockwell), 1864-1938; Skinner, Robert Peet, 1866-1960; Smith, Walter Bedell, 1895-1961; Somoza, Anastasio, 1896-1956; Sonnino, Sidney, 1847-1922; Spellman, Francis, 1889-1967; Sterling, Frederick, 1876-; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950; Sulzberger, Arthur Hays, 1891-1968; Sulzberger, C. L. (Cyrus Leo), 1912-1993; Summerfield, Arthur E. (Arthur Ellsworth), 1899-1972; Summerlin, George Thomas, 1872-1947; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Taylor, Wayne Chatfield, 1893-1967; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961; Thompson, Llewellyn, 1904-1972; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Tully, Grace, 1900-1984; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965; Wallace, Hugh Campbell, 1863-1931; Walsh, Harry L.; Weddell, Alexander Wilbourne, 1876-1948; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961; White, Henry, 1850-1927; Wiley, Alexander, 1884-1967; Wiley, John C. (John Cooper), 1893-1967; Wilson, Charles S. (Charles Stetson), 1873-1947; Wilson, Henry Lane, 1857-1932; Winiewicz, Józef; Wright, J. Butler (Joshua Butler), 1877-1939; Wright, James H.; Intergovernmental Committee for European Migration; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); Yale University -- Students; Yalta Conference ( 1945 I︠A︡lta, Ukraine)
- Letters to Arthur Bliss Lane and to Cornelia Baldwin Lane, 1907-1957; Series I; 274 feet 55 Boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains correspondence to Arthur Bliss Lane from 1907 to 1956, and to Cornelia Baldwin Lane from 1956 to 1957. The letters are arranged chronologically, with undated material at the end.
  Included are official, personal and business communications. Letters and telegrams to Cornelia Baldwin Lane concern Arthur Bliss Lane's death in 1956.
  - 1907-1928 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 1-22)
  - 1928 June 16-1928 [no month] (Box 2, Folder 23-39)
  - 1929 January-1930 January 22 (Box 2, Folder 40-52)
  - 1930 January 23-1930 July 31 (Box 3, Folder 53-72)
  - 1930 August 1-1930 [no month] (Box 4, Folder 73-91)
  - 1931 January 1- 1931 August 21 (Box 5, Folder 92-108)
  - 1931 August 22-1933 February 16 (Box 6, Folder 109-134)
  - 1933 February 17-1933 October (Box 7, Folder 135-153)
  - 1933 November 1-1933 December (Box 8, Folder 154-158)
  - 1934 January 1-1934 April 30 (Box 8, Folder 159-168)
  - 1934 May 1-1934 December (Box 9, Folder 169-185)
  - 1935 January 1-1935 June 20 (Box 10, Folder 186-201)
  - 1935 June 21-1936 January 8 (Box 11, Folder 202-218)
  - 1936 January 9-1936 June 30 (Box 12, Folder 219-237)
  - 1936 July 1-1936 September 19 (Box 13, Folder 238-249)
  - 1936 September 20-1937 March 22 (Box 14, Folder 250-267)
  - 1937 March 23-1937 August 17 (Box 15, Folder 268-287)
  - 1937 August 18-1938 February (Box 16, Folder 288-307)
  - 1938 March 1-1939 November (Box 17, Folder 308-328)
  - 1939 December-1941 December (Box 18, Folder 329-351)
  - 1942 January 1-1942 October (Box 19, Folder 352-367)
  - 1942 November 1-1943 August 17 (Box 20, Folder 368-385)
  - 1943 August 18-1944 August 18 (Box 21, Folder 386-407)
  - 1944 August 19-1944 [no month] (Box 22, Folder 408-419)
  - 1945 January 1-1945 May 31 (Box 22, Folder 420-428)
  - 1945 June 1-1945 December 12 (Box 23, Folder 429-446)
  - 1945 December 13-1945 [no month] (Box 24, Folder 447-450)
  - 1946 January 1-1946 June 5 (Box 24, Folder 451-468)
  - 1946 June 6-1946 December 31 (Box 25, Folder 469-487)
  - 1946 [no month] (Box 26, Folder 488)
  - 1947 January 1-1947 April 10 (Box 26, Folder 489-504)
  - 1947 April 11-1947 April 30 (Box 27, Folder 505-518)
  - 1947 April [no day] (Box 28, Folder 519)
  - 1947 May 1-1947 September 17 (Box 28, Folder 520-533)
  - 1947 September 18-1947 [no month] (Box 29, Folder 534-546)
  - 1948 January 1-1948 January 25 (Box 29, Folder 547-550)
  - 1948 January 26-1948 April 6 (Box 30, Folder 551-565)
  - 1948 April 7-1948 July 19 (Box 31, Folder 566-582)
  - 1948 July 20-1948 October 6 (Box 32, Folder 583-597)
  - 1948 October 7-1948 November 6 (Box 33, Folder 598-602)
  - 1948 November 8-1948 December 22 (Box 33, Folder 603-611)
  - 1948 December 23-1948 [no month] (Box 34, Folder 612-614)
  - 1949 January 1-1949 March 5 (Box 34, Folder 615-627)
  - 1949 March 6-1949 May 3 (Box 35, Folder 628-642)
  - 1949 May 4-1949 July 31 (Box 36, Folder 643-658)
  - 1949 August 1-1949 October 21 (Box 37, Folder 659-673)
  - 1949 October 22-1949 October 31, October [no day] (Box 38, Folder 674-675)
  - 1949 November 1-1950 January 12 (Box 38, Folder 676-687)